Guide to the Guide to the Postal, Telegraph, and Telephone International Collection TAM 099
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
Postal, Telegraph, and Telephone International Collection
1914-1967
TAM 099
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
1.0 Linear feet
The Postal, Telegraph, and Telephone International was formed in 1911 in Bern as the International Federation of Posts, telegraphs, and Telephones. The anti-fascist and anti-communist PTTI eagerly sought the spread of democratic trade unionism and promoted the League of Nations. By the early 1930's, PTTI's membership surged into the hundreds of thousands. Throughout the 1950's and 1960's, the PTTI conducted research on the postal services of newly independent nations of Asia and Africa, and of Latin America and set up regional offices to integrate their postal unions. Today, the PTTI conducts educational programs and hold international conferences. In 1991, PTTI membership was more than four million and based in 65 unions in 102 nations. The collection includes material that documents PTTI's history, its organization and administrative structure.
Provenance
The collection of the Postal, Telegraph, and Telephone International (PTTI) was a gift of Bruno Stein.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Postal, Telegraph, and Telephone International was formed in 1911 in Bern as the International Federation of Posts, telegraphs, and Telephones. However, the official founding conference was not held until 1920 in Milan, when postal employees realized that during World War I, the Post Office was unique in having maintained its international connections, and consequently should be developed as an instrument for world peace. The anti-fascist and anti-communist PTTI eagerly sought the spread of democratic trade unionism. It promoted the League of Nations and tried in its early years to be non-political for fear of a split between those who favored a separate trade union and those who favored affiliation with industrial unions. In the early 1920's, however, the union refused to admit the Soviet Postal Union.
Though always interested in learning from their foreign colleagues and uniting postal workers from all supposedly democratic nations, the discussions in the PTTI in the pre-WWII era seem to reflect concerns with nationalization of the postal services and employee control.
In the early 1930's, PTTI's membership surged into the hundreds of thousands, mainly of unionists from European countries. Because of communication difficulties, the implementation of Esperanto was attempted with some limited success. After 1935, the PTTI lost thousands of members as fascist forces closed PTTI offices in Vienna, Berlin, and other cities.
In 1947, the PTTI joined the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) as an International Trade Secretariat. In 1949, American unions and their allies withdrew from the WFTU because of rising cold-war tensions and disagreement over the Marshall Plan. They formed the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, and the PTTI followed suit.
Throughout the 1950's and 1960's, the PTTI conducted research on the postal services of newly independent nations of Asia and Africa, and of Latin America. The PTTI set up regional offices in these nations to integrate their postal unions into the International and to educate future leaders of the national postal unions.
Today, the PTTI conducts educational programs and hold international conferences. In 1991, PTTI membership was more than four million based in 65 unions in 102 nations.
Scope and Content Note
The 1.0 linear foot collection spans the years 1914-1967, with material evenly dispersed throughout those years. Provided in the collection is good documentation of the activities, structure, and goals of the organization. The collection, consisting mainly of reports, correspondence, bulletins, and indexes, is arranged in chronological order within each series.
Series I, History (1963-1967), contains a chapter outline plus one chapter of an unpublished book on the PTTI. This series also contains a thesis on the PTTI's history, based largely on information found in the collection.
Series II, Administrative Files (1914-1966), contains information generated by the central office of the PTTI, as well as resolutions passed in biennial congresses. Of special note in this series are the materials documenting the controversy surrounding the PTTI's 1924 refusal to admit the Soviet Postal Union.
The information documented this collection reflect the alliances, contradictions, and ideals of the larger international labor movement of this era.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into two series; I: History (1963-1967); II: Administrative Files (1914-1966).
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Separated Material
Postal, Telegraph and Telephone Workers' International.; World Federation of Trade Unions.; Adminstrative records.; Correspondence.; International labor activities.; Labor unions.; News bulletins.; Postal service--Employees--Labor unions.; Postal service--Employees.; Reports.; Telegraphers--Labor unions.; Telegraphers.; Telephone companies--Employees--Labor unions.; Telephone operators.; Typescripts.
- Series I: History (1963-1967)
  - History of the PTTI--Chapter Outline, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - PTTI General Staff Matters--Chapter 5, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Postal, Telegraph, and Telephone Inter-national--1910-1945" Victor Hershkowitz, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Summary from International Directory of the Trade Union Movement., 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Administrative Files (1914-1966)
  - Monthly Bulletin, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Notes of Second Congress--London, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Founding Congress--Milan, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Third Congress--Vienna, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Congress Resolutions, 1920-1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - US Federation of Post Office Clerks, 1921-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - PTTI Reports, 1922-1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Responses to Reports, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence--Russian Union, 1923-1924 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1923-1925 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report on Promotion, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The United Front and the PTT International, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Publications List, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence--League of Nations --Universal Postal Union, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence and Meetings--Russian Union, 1926-1927 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee Meetings, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence of General Secretary, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Report--US National Federation of Postal Clerks, 1926-1930 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Affiliations List, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Fourth Congress--Paris, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fifth Congress--London, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Executive Council Meetings, 1928-1930 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Yearbook, 1929-1930 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sixth Congress--Copenhagen, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Executive Committee Reports, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Yearbook, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Financial Report, 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Excerpts from Post Bulletin, 1931-1935 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Seventh Congress--Lucerne, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Affiliations, 1932-1935 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Vienna Situation, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - German Correspondence, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Letters to PTTI President, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Eighth Congress--Brussels, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Bulletin--International Committee of Clerks, Civil Servants, and Post Office Workers, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Information Bulletin, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Index to Post Bulletins, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Report--"The Regulation of Multiple Employment", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Affiliations, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - International Federation of Trade Unions--Notes, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Excerpts from Post Bulletin, 1936-1940 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Executive Committee Reports, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Reports of International Federation of Employeesin the Public and Civil Service, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Ninth Congress--Paris, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Report on Activities, 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Tenth Congress--Brussels, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - World Trade Union Council--Paris, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Eleventh Congress--London, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - World Federation of Trade Unions, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Annual Account, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Executive Council Report, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Executive Committee Meeting--Dublin, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Study Tour of Eastern European Countries, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Index to Post Bulletins, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Executive Committee Meeting--Zurich, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Post Bulletin, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Index to Post Bulletins, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Congress Resolutions, 1951-1954 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Report--"Avenues of Advancement", 1953 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Executive Committee Meetings--Copenhagen, Vienna, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Report--Study Trip to Africa, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Executive Committee on African, Asian, and Latin American Affairs, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Executive Committee Reports, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - History of the International Labor Movement and ICTFU, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Financial Report, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - PTTI Draft Constitution, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Eighteenth Congress--London, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Reports--eighteenth Congress, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - PTTI Resolutions, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Congress--Brussels, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - PTTI Statutes, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - The British Unions and the PTTI, undated (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - List of Study Reports by PTTI, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Affiliations, undated (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - PTTI Congress Standing Orders, undated (Box 1, Folder 80)